Guide to the Mordecai and Irma Bauman Papers TAM.222
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mordecai and Irma Bauman Papers
1926-2006
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Bauman, Mordecai, 1912-2007
Bauman, Irma, 1915-2014
Perry, Elizabeth Israels
TAM.222
4.45 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 3 manuscript boxes, and 1 half manuscript box.
4 videocassettes (vhs)
3 audiocassette
8 electronic discs (cd-rom)
Mordecai Bauman (1912-2007) was a singer, music educator, concert promoter, and progressive activist. The collection contains correspondence, photographs, ephemera and other materials documenting his association with notables including Marc Blitzstein, Hanns Eisler, and Mrs. Charles Ives, concerts, including benefits for progressive causes, his recording career, his educational work at Brooklyn College and the Bread and Roses Cultural Project, and his documentary, The Stations of Bach.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Mordecai and Irma Bauman between 1999-2004; additional materials were accessioned after 2006. In 2015 Elisabeth Israels Perry sent a photo album and recordings of interviews with Bauman. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1999.005, 1999.008, 1999.010, NPA.2005.036, and 2015.011
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Historical/Biographical Note
Mordecai Bauman (1912-2007) had a long and varied musical career as a singer and recording artist, a music administrator, educator and producer, much of which occurred in the context of progressive and labor movement cultural activity during the 1930s and 1940s. Additionally, he was personally and professionally associated with Hanns Eisler and Marc Blitzstein. Born in the Bronx, New York, Bauman received degrees from the Julliard School of Music (1934), Columbia University (B.A., 1935), and Case Western Reserve University (M.A., 1949). From 1952 to 1975 he was the founder and owner, with his wife Irma Commanday Bauman, of the Indian Hill, a summer workshop in the arts in Stockbridge, Massachusetts, which he then donated to Brooklyn College, where he was Professor of Music. From 1970 to 1972 he was managing director of Symphony Hall (Newark, NJ). Bauman was the founding director of the Bread and Roses Project, the ongoing cultural program of District 1199, National Union of Hospital and Health Care Employees. Bauman also conceived and produced The Stations of Bach (1990) a documentary filmed in Germany, and recorded the collaborative works of Bertolt Brecht and Hanns Eisler, the works of Charles Ives, and American folk, labor and popular songs.
Source: Bauman, Irma and Mordecai. From our angle of repose: a memoir. New York City: "Privately published for our friends & family," 2006. 526 p.: ill., ports.
Related Material
The Indian Hill Records, 1952-1976, 15 boxes, are located at the Stockbridge (Massachusetts) Library Association.
The Mordecai Bauman Collection of Political Music and Papers, 1914-1952, two boxes, is at the New York Public Library for the Performing Arts (Music Division).
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains clippings, concert programs, correspondence, ephemera, memorabilia, and photographs, which document Mordecai Bauman's education and musical career. Principal and/or prominent correspondents include: Joseph Abilieah (Society for Middle East Confederation), Irma Commanday Bauman, Betty Bean (American-Soviet Musical Society), Marc Blitzstein, Ronald D. Cohen (folk/left music historian), Congressmen Silvio Conte and Robert Drinan, Barker Fairley, Victor Grossman, Mrs. Charles Ives, Peter Janz (Berlin), Charles Panzera, Samuel Puner, Eberhard Rebling (East Berlin), Werner Schmidt (Dresden Art Museum). Also included in the collection are a photo album and memorabilia from Bauman's service in World War II, as well as recordings of Bauman's interviews and performances from the 1980s and 1990s. Interviews feature discussions of Bauman's musical career and the works of Bertolt Brecht and Hanns Eisler.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Separated Material
Sixteen audiocassettes (interviews, lectures, radio programs) have been separated to the Library's audio collections, and established as Mordecai Bauman Audiocassettes (OH 055).
Communism and music.; Baritones -- (Singers) -- United States -- Biography.; Photographs.; Political ballads and songs -- United States.; Programs (documents); Printed ephemera.; Correspondence.; Music -- Political aspects -- United States.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Veterans.; Society for Middle East Confederation; Brooklyn College. Department of Music; Indian Hill Music Camp (Stockbridge, Mass.); Janz, Peter; Ives, Harmony Twichell; Puner, Samuel.; Panzéra, Charles, 1896-1976; Schmidt, Werner, 1910-; Rebling, Eberhard, 1911-2008; Bread and Roses Cultural Project; American-Soviet Musical Society; Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-1956; Cohen, Ronald D., 1940-; Bean, Betty; Blitzstein, Marc; Abilieah, Joseph.; Grossman, Victor, 1928-; Fairley, Barker, 1887-1986; Eisler, Hanns, 1898-1962; Dvorakova, Karolina; Dvořák, Stanislav; Drinan, Robert F.; Conte, Silvio O. (Silvio Ottavio), 1921-1991; Perry, Elizabeth Israels
- Abileah, Joseph: Correspondence (Society for Middle East Confederation), 1968-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- American Enterprise, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- American Music, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Anne Frank, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Armstrong, Louis, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bach: Newsletters and Article, 1998-2002 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Bach, the Stations of: Correspondence, 1981-1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Bach, the Stations of: Correspondence and General Files, 1995-2004 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Bach, the Stations of: NEH Proposal, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Bach Tour: Leipzig, Germany, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bauman: Autobiographical Typescript, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1948-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Bauman: CIA & FBI: Files & FOIA Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bauman: Education, Military, and Marriage Documents, 1934-1951 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Bauman: Fifty-Three Review(Yearbook, P.S. 53, Bronx, NY), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Bauman: High School Yearbook, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Bauman: Interviews, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Bauman: Interview and Performances, 1980s - 1990s (Box 7)
- Bauman: Miscellaneous Projects, Proposals, etc., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Bauman: Photographs, 1929-1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Bauman: Writings, Unpublished, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Bean, Betty: Correspondence (Includes American-Soviet Musical Society), 1947-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- The Beggar's Opera: Photographs, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Blitzstein, Marc: Cleveland Concert, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Blitzstein, Marc: Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Blitzstein, Marc: Ephemera, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Blitzstein, Marc: Ephemera, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Blitzstein, Marc: Letters to Mordecai and Irene Bauman, 1942-1948 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Blitzstein, Marc: Letters to Mordecai and Irene Bauman, 1951-1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Blitzstein, Marc: Memorial Concert, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Blitzstein, Marc: Music, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Blitzstein, Marc: Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Blitzstein, Marc: "The Cradle Will Rock", 1967-1997 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Bread & Roses, 1978-1998 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Berliner Ensemble: Brochures and Ephemera, 1979-1998 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Brecht, Bertolt, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Brooklyn College: Employment Termination Dispute, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Brooklyn College: Music Grows in Brooklyn (radio program), 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Chicago 1893: Grant Proposal and Research Files, 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Clippings: General, circa 1995-2000 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Cohen, Ronald D.: Correspondence, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Columbia University, 1930-1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Concert Programs, 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Concert Programs, 1934-2005 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Concert Programs, 1941-1950 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Concert Programs, 1951-1967 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Concert Programs, 1978-1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Conte, Silvio O. (Congressman, D-Massachusetts): Correspondence, 1966-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, General, 1937-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, General, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Davis, Ron G., 1986-1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Day, James: Correspondence, 1994-1998 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Drinan, Robert F. (Congressman, D-Massachusetts): Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Dumling, Albert, 1987-1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Dvorak, Stanislav & Karolina Dvorakova: Correspondence, 1949-1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Eisler, Hanns, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Eisler, Hanns: Clippings for The Last Generation, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Eisler, Hanns: General Files, circa 1982-1998 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Eisler, Hanns: General Files, circa 1983-1998 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Eisler, Hanns: German-Language General Files, circa 1990-2000 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Eisler, Hanns: More Than a Fair Trial - The Un-American Activities Committee Case Against Hanns Eisler, by John Highkin, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Eisler, Hanns: More Than a Fair Trial - The Un-American Activities Committee Case Against Hanns Eisler, by John Highkin, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Eisler, Hanns: Programs, 1947-1998 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Eisler, Hanns: Solidarity Song, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Eisler, Hanns: Solidarity Song Correspondence, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Eislermateriel, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Eisler Mitteilungen, 1994-2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Eisler Mitteilungen, Oct 1997-Jul 2001 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Eisler Mitteilungen, Feb 2002-Jun 2003 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Eisler Mitteilungen, Oct 2003-Jun 2006 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Fairley, Barker: Correspondence, Ephemera, 1966-1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Fifty Years of American Music (Bauman Seminar at Hampshire College), 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Film und Fernsehen, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Folk Music Concert, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Grossman, Victor (AKA Stephen Wechsler), 1978-1997 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Indian Hill, 1975-2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Ives, Charles (Mrs.): Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Ives, Charles: Centennial, Other, 1960-1978 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Janz, Peter (Berlin): Correspondence, 1988-1996 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Makers of America(unproduced TV music series), undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Menuhin, Yehudi: Project, Correspondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1931-1935 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1941-1943 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1952-1971 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Miscellaneous Clippings, Ephemera, Other, 1977-1998 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Mr. Pepys: A Ballad Opera (notebook), undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Mr. Pepy's: A Ballad Opera (Photographs), undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Notes: General, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Older Adults: A Proposal for a Cultural Center, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Panzera, Charles: Correspondence, 1948-1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Paul Bunyan, circa 1977-1993 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Paul Bunyan (opera), 1941-1998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Photographs, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Puner, Samuel Paul (recording executive): Correspondence, 1947-1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Radio Programs, 1940-1946 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Rattner, Abraham (painter): Correspondence, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Rebling, Prof. Eberhard & Jalda (Berlin): Correspondence, 1978-1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Recordings: Clippings, Ephemera, 1938-1941 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Right On (film, starring the Last Poets): Correspondence, 1968-1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Rosen, Paul: Correspondence (re La Traviata, etc.), 1948-1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Schmidt, Werner (Dresden Art Museum): Correspondence, 1978-1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Stern, Bernard (British painter): Correspondence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Stern, Bernard: Photographs, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Stretta: A Work in Progress, circa 1999 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Symphony Hall, Newark NJ: Bauman Resigns as Managing Director, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- U.S. Army, 1942-1947, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- U.S. Army: World War II Scrapbook and Memorabilia, 1942-1945 (Box 6)
- Weill, Kurt, 1983-1992 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Wolff, Christoff: Clippings and Correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)